Guide to the Communications Workers of America, Local 2150 Records WAG.229
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communications Workers of America, Local 2150 Records
1944-2002, (Bulk 1970s-1990s)
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communications Workers of America. Local 2150
Wolf, Elaine
WAG.229
6 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
Communications Workers of America, Local 2150 represented AT&T Long Lines (long distance) employees in the Baltimore, MD area. Among the matters of special concern to the local were jurisdictional matters, and health and safety issues in the workplace. The collection includes correspondence of the Local's officers and several committees; minutes of Executive Board, membership and stewards meetings; and subject files containing materials concerning most aspects of the Local's activities. NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Communications Workers of America, Local 2150, through an agreement with president Elaine Wolf, in 2003. The accession number associated with this gift is 2003.033.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Local 2150 was chartered as a Communications Workers of America (CWA) Local in 1949, but its origins can be traced to the Bell Systems company unions of the 1920s. In 1935, the passage of the Wagner Act the Long Lines employees in Maryland were organized into Long Lines Local 16, a group of the Long Lines American Union. Each of the Long Lines Locals sent a representative to meet with the Bell System's Vice-President of Long Lines concerning their own grievances. The Bell System management was thus able to pit one local against another, and avoid being pressured into making changes beneficial to workers. This prompted the formation of the National Federation of Telephone Workers (NFTW), of which the Baltimore local was a part.
Following the formation of the NFTW, the Baltimore long-lines local was known as Local 16, NFTW. Other groups of telephone workers in the same geographical area had their own locals and barahined separately with their own management. Local 16 was very small, with its officers forced to conduct business out of their homes. The widespread telephone strike of 1947 was an ordeal, a catalyst for growth, and a point of fracture for the union. The local drew up a schedule, and manned the picket lines daily throughout the six-week strike. During the strike, the much larger Chesapeake & Potomac Traffic Division's union invited Local 16 to share its headquarters for a nominal fee, giving the union access to its own office space for the first time. Despite this advance and the settlement of the strike, there was growing dissention within the NFTW.
In the aftermath of the 1947 strike, there evolved two groups. Joe Beirne of the Western Electric Sales Union wanted to form an independent national union, the Communications Workers of America. Jack Moran, president of the New York Long Lines disagreed and sought to join the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO), forming the Telephone Workers Organizing Committee (TWOC) -CIO. Local 16 sided with Moran, once again undergoing a change of name to Local 16, TWOC-CIO.
In 1949, the CWA finally joined the CIO. This prompted one final name change for the Baltimore-area long-lines union. The organization was designated Local 2150, CWA-CIO. The numbers represented the district and type of workers the Local represented. The 2 designated the Local's District, 1 indicateded that this was the district's first Long Lines local, and 50 is the union's code for Long Lines employees. Local 2150's charter gave it jurisdiction over all Long Lines offices in the state of Maryland. It represents members from Baltimore, Elkton, Fairlee, Finksburg, Frostburg, Hagerstown, Randallstown, and Waldorf.
The scattering of membership across the state sometimes proved to be a hindrance to representation of members by the union's officers. It was hard for a few officers and staff to effectively address the particular grievances of these far-flung offices and operations. This siruation persisted until the 1960s, when the office of Chief Locality Steward was created. These were to be the highest-ranking union official in each office, dealing directly with the various operations managers. This allowed the Local's president and vice-president to deal with the district managers and the CWA International.
In 1973, Local 2150 became involved in a dispute with CWA Local 2350 over the right to organize workers in Waldorf, MD. The contending locals turned to the international union, which, after reviewing the arguments, ruled in favor of Local 2350. In 2003, after a period of waning membership numbers, Local 2150 was merged with a CWA local based in Virginia.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Minutes, contains minutes of Executive Board, and General Membership and other meetings.
Series II: Correspondence, contains correspondence between the Local headquarters and various individuals and organizations, among them CWA District 2, CWA international headquarters, AT&T and other Long Lines locals. This series also includes the correspondence of the Locality Stewards.
Series III: Subject Files, contains files concerning the activities and interests of Local 2150. These include AT&T divestiture and reorganization, the Local's bylaw and charter documents, training manuals and handbooks, the Local's newsletter Cross Talk, member resignations, organizing, officer recall, various workplace health and safety issues, and the records of various strikes.
NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically within each series.
The files are grouped into three series:
Missing Title
I, Minutes
II, Correspondence
III, Subject Files
American Telephone and Telegraph Company -- Employees.; Minutes (administrative records); Labor unions -- Telecommunication -- United States.; Strikes and lockouts -- Telecommunication.; Collective labor agreements -- Telecommunication.; Legal documents.; Labor unions -- Contract administration.; Fliers (printed matter); Baltimore (Md.); Telecommunication -- United States -- History.; Labor unions -- Officials and employees.; Telecommunication -- Employees -- United States.; Maryland.; Correspondence.; Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.; Arbitration, Industrial.; American Telephone and Telegraph Company; Bell Telephone Company; Communications Workers of America. District 2; Communications Workers of America. Local 2150; Wolf, Elaine
- Series I: Minutes, 1946-2002
  - Executive Board, 1946-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Executive Board, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Executive Board, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Executive Board, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Executive Board, 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Executive Board, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1947-1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1960-1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - General Membership Meetings, 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Long Lines/American Telephone & Telegraph (AT&T) Safety Committee Meetings, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Quality Work Life (QWL) Committee, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Stewards Meetings, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1944-1994
  - Correspondence: AT&T Communications (ATTCOM), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence: Department of Labor, US, Jun 1968 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence: District 2, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence: District 2, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence: District 2, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence: District 2, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: District 2, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: District 2, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: District 2, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: District 2, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: District 2, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: District 2 Vice-President, 1972-1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Eastern Area Long Lines Caucus (EALLC), 1979-1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: International Headquarters, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: International Headquarters, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: International Headquarters, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Joint Safety Advisory Committee, 1972-1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Locality Stewards, 1963-1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Long Lines Division, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Long Lines Division, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Long Lines Division, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Long Lines Division 10, CWA-CIO Local 16, 1944-1955 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Long Lines Safety Committee, 1981-1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: National, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: National, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: National, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: National, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: National, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: National, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: National, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: National, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Other Local Presidents, 1984-1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: State, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: State, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: State, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: State, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Stewards, 1961-1983 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Technology, 1982-1989 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Series III: Subject Files, 1949-2002
  - AT&T Communications (ATTCOM) Mobilization Committee, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - AT&T Employee Survey, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - AT&T Mobilization Committee, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - AT&T Reorganization Plan, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - AT&T Settlement Memorandum, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Apple Seed: Move to Cockeysville, MD, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Bylaws: Amendments, 1951-1988 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Charter Certificates, 1949-1963 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Charter Review, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Chief Locality Steward's Book, Undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Company Labor Relations Handbook, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Communications Workers of America Operations Settlement Memorandum, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Concerned Communities against AT&T Closings, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Convention Binder, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Cross Talk (Local Newsletter), 1964-1984 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Cross Talk (Local Newsletter), 1985-1988 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Cross Talk (Local Newsletter), 1989-2002 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Decertification, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Displaced Workers Programs, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Free State Caucus, 1987-1991 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Health and Safety: Asbestos, 1984-1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Health and Safety: Dust Exposure-Hagerstown, MD, Feb 1982 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Health and Safety: PCB Leak-Hagerstown, MD, 1980-1982 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Health and Safety: Manhole Safety, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Health and Safety: Toxic Dust-Hagerstown, MD, 1981-1985 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Hearing: Member Walkout, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Hearing: Parker, Bonnie D., 1970 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (IBEW): Memorandum of Understanding, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Job Responsibility: AT&T Campaign, 1962-1973 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Joint Safety Advisory Committee, National, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Joint Safety Advisory Committee, National, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Joint Safety Advisory Committee, National, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Legal: Failure to Provide Information, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Local Agreements, 1993-1997 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Local Bylaws, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Local Secretary Manual, 1969-1982 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Local Trial Board, 1950-1981 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Local Trial Procedures, 1984-1987 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Member Resignations, 1950-1966 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Member Resignations, 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Member Resignations, 1970-1973 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Member Resignations, 1976-1984 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Member Resignations, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Member Resignations, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Member Resignations, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Member Resignations, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Member Resignations, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Member Resignations, 1996-1998 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Member Resignations, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Member Resignations: Contested-Greene, Ronald W., 1983 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Member Resignations: Contested-Gregorich, John, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Member Resignations: Contested-Pellant, Joseph, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Member Resignations: Contested-Timberlake, Maxwell, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Members Crossing Picket Lines, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Members Crossing Picket Lines, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Monitoring, 1974-1977 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Monitoring, 1988-1991 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - National Convention, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - National Labor Relations Board (NLRB) Case: Mass Suspensions, Jun 1969 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - NLRB Charges: Berkshire Corporation, AT&T, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - NLRB Charges: Parr, Melody-Crossing Picket Lines, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - NLRB: Traffic Employees, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - National Units Conference, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) Complaint: Company Vehicle-Faulkner, MD, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - OSHA Training Manual, Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Organizing, 1980-1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Organizing Manual, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Quality Work Life (QWL) Steering Committee, 1988-1990 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Recall of Local Officers: Ramey, Eric, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Recording, Locals, 1985-1991 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Safety Plan: General Instruction #36, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Seton Hall University Survey, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Smoking Policy, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Solidarity Day, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Stewards Meetings, 1981-1983 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Steward Resignations, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Stewards Newsletter, 1971-1985 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Steward Training, 1981-1985 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Stress Survey, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Strike, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Strike, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Strike, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Strike: Picketing CEO Robert Allen's House, Sep 1990 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Strike, Threatened, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Strike, Threatened, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Strike, Threatened-National Long Lines, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Supervisor Evaluations: Baltimore/Eastern Shore, MD, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Supervisor Evaluations: Central Maryland, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Supervisor Evaluations: Hagerstown/Faulkner, MD, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Supervisor Evaluations: Southern Maryland, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Surveys, 1972-1988 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Telephone Conversation Log, 1982-1991 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Union Policies, 1967-1983 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Video Display Terminal and Repetitive Motion Injury Survey, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Wage Freeze, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Waldorf, MD Jurisdiction Dispute (with CWA Local 2350), 1973 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Work Jurisdiction Disputes, 1981-1988 (Box 6, Folder 37)